In 2012, when I painted the minaret of Jara Mosque
في عام 2012 ،عندما قمت برسم مئذنة مسجد جارا
in my hometown of Gabés, in the south of Tunisia,
في مسقط رأسي في قابس، في جنوب تونس،لم أظن أبداً أن الكتابة
I never thought that graffiti would bring so much attention to a city.
على الجدر قد تجلب الاهتمام إلى المدينة.
At the beginning, I was just looking for a wall in my hometown,
في البداية ،كنت أبحث فقط عن حائط للرسم عليه في بلدتي ،
and it happened that the minaret was built in '94.
وما حدث أن المئذنة بنيت في عام 94.
And for 18 years, those 57 meters of concrete stayed grey.
وعلى مدى 18 عاماً، بقيت تلك 57 متراً من الخرسانة على لونها الرمادي.
When I met the imam for the first time, and I told him what I wanted to do,
عندما التقيت الإمام لأول مرة، وقلت له ما أردت القيام به،
he was like, "Thank God you finally came,"
كان لسان حاله "الحمد لله أنك جئت في نهاية المطاف،"
and he told me that for years he was waiting for somebody
وأخبرني أنه ومنذ سنوات ينتظر أحدهم
to do something on it.
ليفعل شيئاً لهذه المئذنة .
The most amazing thing about this imam is that he didn't ask me anything --
الشيء الأكثر دهشة حول هذا الإمام أنه لم يطلب مني شيئاً -
neither a sketch, or what I was going to write.
يتعلق بالرسم أو ما كنت أود كتابته .
In every work that I create, I write messages
في كل عمل أقوم به أكتب رسالة
with my style of calligraffiti -- a mix of calligraphy and graffiti.
مع أسلوبي الخطي الخاص المكون من مزيج من الخط والكتابة على الجدران.
I use quotes or poetry.
أستخدم فيها الاقتباس أو الشعر .
For the minaret, I thought that the most relevant message
بالنسبة للمئذنة ،أعتقد أن أكثر رسالة ذات صلة
to be put on a mosque should come from the Quran,
يمكن وضعها على المسجد يجب أن تكون من القرآن الكريم ،
so I picked this verse:
لذلك اخترت هذه الآية:
"Oh humankind, we have created you from a male and a female,
"ياأيها االناس،إناخلقناكم من ذكر وأنثى،
and made you people and tribe, so you may know each other."
وجعلناكم شعوباً وقبائل لتعارفوا
It was a universal call for peace, tolerance, and acceptance
"لقد كانت دعوة عالمية للسلام، التسامح، والقبول
coming from the side that we don't usually portray in a good way in the media.
أتت من ذلك الجانب الذي عادةً لا نقوم فيه بالتصوير بطريقة جيدة في الإعلام .
I was amazed to see how the local community reacted to the painting,
لقد كان مذهلاً أن ترى كيف كانت ردة فعل السكان المحلين على هذه الرسومات ،
and how it made them proud to see the minaret getting so much attention
وكيف جعلهم ذلك فخورين لرؤية المئذنة تحصل على كل هذا الاهتمام
from international press all around the world.
من الصحافة الدولية حول العالم .
For the imam, it was not just the painting;
بالنسبة للإمام ،لم تكن مجرد رسومات ;
it was really deeper than that.
بل كانت بالفعل أعمق من ذلك .
He hoped that this minaret would become a monument for the city,
وأعرب عن أمله أن هذه المئذنة ستصبح نصبا تذكاريا للمدينة،
and attract people to this forgotten place of Tunisia.
وجذب الناس إلى هذا المكان المنسي من تونس.
The universality of the message,
عالمية الرسالة،
the political context of Tunisia at this time,
السياق السياسي لتونس في هذا الوقت،
and the fact that I was writing Quran in a graffiti way
وحقيقة أنني كنت أكتب القرآن بطريقة الكتابة على الجدران
were not insignificant.
لم تكن تافهة.
It reunited the community.
بل إنها لمت شمل المجتمع.
Bringing people, future generations,
التقريب بين الناس، وأجيال المستقبل،
together through Arabic calligraphy
معا من خلال الخط العربي
is what I do.
هو ما أقوم به .
Writing messages is the essence of my artwork.
كتابة الرسائل هو جوهر أعمالي الفنية.
What is funny, actually, is that even Arabic-speaking people
ما هو مضحك، في الواقع، هو أنه حتى الناطقين باللغة العربية
really need to focus a lot to decipher what I'm writing.
بحاجة إلى التركيز كثيراً لفك شيفرة ما أكتبه .
You don't need to know the meaning to feel the piece.
أنت في غنى عن معرفة المعنى لقطعة تشعر بها .
I think that Arabic script touches your soul before it reaches your eyes.
أعتقد أن اللغة العربية تلمس روحك قبل أن تلمس عينيك .
There is a beauty in it that you don't need to translate.
هناك جمال فيها لا يحتاج ترجمة.
Arabic script speaks to anyone, I believe;
الخط العربي يتحدث إلى أي شخص، وأعتقد؛ أنه
to you, to you, to you, to anybody,
لك، لك، لك، ولأي أحد ،
and then when you get the meaning,
ثم عندما تحصل على معنى،
you feel connected to it.
تشعر بارتباطك بها .
I always make sure to write messages
أنا دائماً أتأكد من إرسال الرسائل
that are relevant to the place where I'm painting,
ذات الصلة إلى المكان في المكان الذي أرسم به ،
but messages that have a universal dimension,
لكن الرسائل التي لها بعد عالمي،
so anybody around the world can connect to it.
تمكن أي شخص في جميع أنحاء العالم الاتصال بها.
I was born and raised in France, in Paris,
لقد ولدت وترعرعت في فرنسا، في باريس،.
and I started learning how to write and read Arabic when I was 18.
وبدأت تعلم الكتابة وقراءة اللغة العربية عندما كان عمري 18 سنة.
Today I only write messages in Arabic.
اليوم أنا أكتب فقط الرسائل باللغة العربية.
One of the reasons this is so important to me,
واحد أهم الأسباب في أن ذلك مهم بالنسبة لي ،
is because of all the reaction that I've experienced all around the world.
هو ردود الأفعال التي عشتها في جميع أنحاء العالم.
In Rio de Janeiro, I translated this Portuguese poem
في ريو دي جانيرو، قمت بترجمة هذه القصيدة البرتغالية
from Gabriela Tôrres Barbosa,
من غابرييلا توريس باربوسا،
who was giving an homage to the poor people of the favela,
الذي كانت يعطي ولاء واحترام للفقراء من فافيلا،
and then I painted it on the rooftop.
وبعد ذلك رسمتها على السطح.
The local community were really intrigued by what I was doing,
كان المجتمع المحلي حقاً مفتونا بما كنت أفعله،
but as soon as I gave them the meaning of the calligraphy,
ولكن سرعان ما أعطيتهم معنى الخط،
they thanked me, as they felt connected to the piece.
وجهوا الشكر لي، كما أنهم شعروا أنهم متصلون بالقطعة .
In South Africa, in Cape Town,
في جنوب أفريقيا، في كيب تاون،.
the local community of Philippi
المجتمع المحلي من فيلبي
offered me the only concrete wall of the slum.
عرض علي الجدار الخرساني الوحيد في الأحياء الفقيرة.
It was a school, and I wrote on it
وكانت مدرسة ،وقمت بكتابة
a quote from Nelson Mandela,
اقتباس من نيلسون مانديلا عليها ،
saying, "[in Arabic],"
"[باللغة العربية]"
which means, "It seems impossible until it's done."
وهو ما يعني، "يبدو من المستحيل حتى يتم ذلك ".
Then this guy came to me and said, "Man, why you don't write in English?"
ثم جاء هذا الرجل وقال لي، ، لماذا لا تكتب باللغة الإنجليزية؟"
and I replied to him, "I would consider your concern legit if you asked me
وأجبته، "أود أن يكون قلقكم شرعي إذا طلب مني
why I didn't write in Zulu."
لماذا لم أكتب بلغة الزولو ".
In Paris, once, there was this event,
في باريس، مرة واحدة، كان هناك هذا الحدث،
and someone gave his wall to be painted.
وأعطى شخص جدار مكتبه لأقوم بالرسم عليه .
And when he saw I was painting in Arabic,
وعندما رأى أني كنت أرسم باللغة العربية ،
he got so mad -- actually, hysterical -- and he asked for the wall to be erased.
جن جنونه ،في الواقع أصابته حالة هستيرية وطلب أن يمحى ما كتب على الحائط .
I was mad and disappointed.
كنت حزيناً ومصاباً بخيبة أمل .
But a week later, the organizer of the event asked me to come back,
ولكن في وقت لاحق في الأسبوع، منظم الحدث طلب مني أن أعود،
and he told me that there was a wall right in front of this guy's house.
وقال لي أن هناك جدار أمام منزل هذا الرجل مباشرة.
So, this guy --
لذلك، هذا الرجل -
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
like, was forced to see it every day.
اضطر لرؤيتها كل يوم.
At the beginning, I was going to write, "[In Arabic],"
في البداية، كنت ذاهباً للكتابة "[باللغة العربية]"
which means, "In your face," but --
وهو ما يعني، "في وجهك"، ولكن -
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
I decided to be smarter and I wrote, "[In Arabic],"
قررت أن أكون أكثر ذكاء وكتبت "[باللغة العربية]"
which means, "Open your heart."
ما معناه ، "افتح قلبك".
I'm really proud of my culture,
أنا فخور حقاً بثقافتي،
and I'm trying to be an ambassador of it through my artwork.
وأنا أحاول أن أكون سفيراً لها من خلال أعمالي الفنية.
And I hope that I can break the stereotypes we all know,
وآمل أن أتمكن من كسر الصور النمطية التي نعلمها جميعاً،
with the beauty of Arabic script.
مع جمال الخط العربي.
Today, I don't write the translation of the message anymore on the wall.
اليوم، أنا لا أكتب ترجمة الرسالة نهائياً على الحائط.
I don't want the poetry of the calligraphy to be broken,
لا أريد لجمال الشعر الموجود في الخط أن يفقد جماله ،
as it's art and you can appreciate it without knowing the meaning,
وبما أن هذا فن ويمكنك أن تقدره دون حتى أن تفهم معناه ،
as you can enjoy any music from other countries.
مثلما يمكنك الاستمتاع لأي موسيقى من بلدان أخرى.
Some people see that as a rejection or a closed door,
بعض الناس يرون ذلك كما لو كان رفضا أو بابا مغلقا،
but for me, it's more an invitation --
ولكن بالنسبة لي، هي دعوة -
to my language, to my culture, and to my art.
للغتي، لثقافتي، وفني.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)